<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ercan Akyürek</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/</link><description>Recent content on Ercan Akyürek</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ercanakyuerek.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building the Easiest Possible Track</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/4-building-the-smallest-possible-track/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/4-building-the-smallest-possible-track/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;To visualize motion properly, we need something for our little object to move along. And that means we need a track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we focus on an extremely simplified roller coaster track. And when I say extremely simplified, I really mean it: it&amp;rsquo;s just a plane. A straight line. A first-order curve. Basically the easiest form of track you can possibly build without accidentally creating a real coaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the last chapter, we know how motion evaluation works. The evaluation function receives an acceleration value and returns a new simulation state containing the updated velocity and the total distance traveled:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Evaluating Motion</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/3-evaluating-motion/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/3-evaluating-motion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before we implement the function, there&amp;rsquo;s one small simplification we need to mention:
In this chapter we will always evaluate the motion every &lt;strong&gt;16 ms (0.016 seconds)&lt;/strong&gt;,
which corresponds to roughly &lt;strong&gt;60 frames per second&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a fixed time step makes the formulas easier to understand for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: In real simulations or game engines, you usually don’t assume a constant time value. Instead, you take the actual delta time from the game loop, so that the motion stays consistent even if the frame rate changes. &lt;strong&gt;More on that later&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Friction and Air Resistance</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/5-friction-and-air-resistance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/5-friction-and-air-resistance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This chapter will be quite short and introduces two small but important parts of a more realistic roller coaster simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;friction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;air resistance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now our coaster moved in a world without any energy loss. That works for understanding the basics but real coasters slow down over time. Wheels create friction, air pushes against the train, and both effects reduce the acceleration the train can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will not create a complex physics model. Instead we introduce two simple parameters, very similar to what you may know from &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Our physics simulation should behave almost identically, apart from a few edge cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gravity</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/2-gravity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/2-gravity/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="how-do-we-determine-the-acceleration-of-the-coaster"&gt;How do we determine the acceleration of the coaster?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To simplify things, we ignore air resistance, rolling friction and any other additional forces. We also assume Earth’s gravity is &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s²&lt;/strong&gt;. This allows us to focus entirely on the fundamental idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gravity is the primary source of acceleration.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Earth, gravity provides a constant acceleration of roughly &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s²&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this number actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt;, an object&amp;rsquo;s speed increases by &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Introduction and Motion Dynamics</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/1-introduction-and-motion-dynamics/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/1-introduction-and-motion-dynamics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You might have played around with JavaScript animations or small physics experiments before, but in this series we are going to take things a step further. We will build a simplified roller coaster simulation directly in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal here isn’t to build some engineering-grade physics engine. I just want to recreate the kind of coaster &lt;strong&gt;physics&lt;/strong&gt; we all know from things like &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster or other coasters in games&lt;/strong&gt;.
Nothing overly scientific, just the kind of system that behaves the way we intuitively expect.
In the end, the physics model will end up pretty close to what &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster&lt;/strong&gt; does anyway, just without all the heavy engineering baggage.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>First results and improved spline interpolation</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/improved-spline-interpolation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:30:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/improved-spline-interpolation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the latest update I tracked down a couple of bugs that caused all those tiny jitters I
mentioned earlier. At first I thought they were just floating-point problems coming from
the WebAssembly module in the browser, but the real issue turned out to be the
&lt;strong&gt;roll interpolation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give you a quick overview of what’s going on. When we interpolate a NURBS track,
we first estimate the total track length using a pretty rough step size. Based on that
estimation, we generate a dense enough set of nodes. After that, we compute normals for
e very node and apply the normal angles on the &lt;strong&gt;x&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; axes, the &lt;strong&gt;z&lt;/strong&gt; axis (the roll)
comes later. These normals get applied to the previous matrix, so the whole orientation
flows along the track. Once that’s done, we generate a &lt;strong&gt;C2-continuous cubic spline&lt;/strong&gt;, and
the z-rotation that results from applying the x/y normals is added to the roll value at
each roll point.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript module</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/4-javascript-module/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 17:45:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/4-javascript-module/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the point where we will develop our &lt;code&gt;JavaScript&lt;/code&gt; library that utilizes the functions exposed in the &lt;code&gt;WebAssembly&lt;/code&gt; module. I have created a simple template for this purpose. You may notice that we are defining some imports for &lt;code&gt;WASI&lt;/code&gt;, but they are all empty. Allow me to explain what &lt;code&gt;WASI&lt;/code&gt; is and what it aims to achieve. &lt;code&gt;WASI&lt;/code&gt; is an attempt to create specifications similar to the &lt;code&gt;POSIX&lt;/code&gt; standard, which can be implemented across different runtimes, such as browsers or regular machines, and provides access to system-specific functions, such as file systems. However, for our library, which only needs to perform calculations, we do not require a complex runtime environment. This is why our functions are empty. Some may argue that we should use the Emscripten SDK instead of the &lt;code&gt;WASI SDK&lt;/code&gt;, but I believe that the &lt;code&gt;WASI SDK&lt;/code&gt; is the future. It produces smaller binaries and has fewer complications compared to &lt;code&gt;Emscripten&lt;/code&gt;. There are official efforts to import standard &lt;code&gt;WASI&lt;/code&gt; functions for the &lt;code&gt;browser&lt;/code&gt;, but unfortunately, they do not seem to work unless a &lt;code&gt;WebAssembly module&lt;/code&gt; is instantiated within a &lt;code&gt;worker&lt;/code&gt;. If there are any changes in the future regarding this matter, I will update my articles accordingly. &lt;a href="https://github.com/wasmerio/wasmer-js"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the mentioned attempt to bring a &lt;code&gt;WASI runtime&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;browsers&lt;/code&gt;. If you can load a &lt;code&gt;WASM file&lt;/code&gt; outside the &lt;code&gt;worker&lt;/code&gt;, just email me your solution and I will include it here! &amp;#x1f604;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementing library functions</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/3-implementing-library-functions/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 00:19:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/3-implementing-library-functions/</guid><description>&lt;div class="embedded-iframe float-right"&gt;

 
 &lt;a href="https://ercanakyuerek.de//wasi-sdk-writing-library-in-cpp/spline.html" class="openInNewTab" style="width: 225px" target="_blank"&gt;Click here to open in a new tab&lt;/a&gt;
 

 &lt;iframe
 src="https://ercanakyuerek.de//wasi-sdk-writing-library-in-cpp/spline.html"
 width="225px"
 height="225px"
 style="border: 0"
 class="iframe"
 &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

 
 &lt;div class="description" style="width: 225px"&gt;Transition from parameter-based non-uniform to uniform node spacing. The control points are draggable.&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll be exploring a more interesting example where we&amp;rsquo;ll construct a Bézier curve, evaluate nodes on it, and write a function that gives any position on the curve by a length parameter. To explain briefly, a Bézier curve is represented by a parameter &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;, which varies between 0 and 1 and determines the position of nodes on the curve. However, this &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt; value doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce uniform spacing, which is problematic when we want to evaluate a point on the curve based on its distance. To solve this, we can evaluate some nodes along the curve with known distances and then linearly interpolate new nodes between them to find the point we&amp;rsquo;re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CMake and build scripts</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/2-cmake-and-build-scripts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 23:15:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/2-cmake-and-build-scripts/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;To simplify the building process, we can create a build script. We have already defined some scripts in our &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file. At this point, the &lt;code&gt;build-wasm.js&lt;/code&gt; file is still empty, so we can create a basic script that first deletes an existing &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; folder, creates a new one, and runs &lt;code&gt;cmake ..&lt;/code&gt; inside it. We will be using a WASI-SDK docker image from &lt;code&gt;ghcr.io/webassembly/wasi-sdk&lt;/code&gt; to run cmake and eventually compile the project via &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Folder structure</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/1-folder-structure/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 22:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/wasi/1-folder-structure/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You may have already heard that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to write certain parts of your web application using languages like C++ or Rust and compile them into WebAssembly. WebAssembly is a binary format that allows code to be executed on the web and is designed to be efficient, secure, and portable. There are use cases where WebAssembly can be particularly beneficial, such as performing complex and resource-intensive computations for real-time applications or mathematical operations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/about/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class="avatar"&gt;
 &lt;img src="https://ercanakyuerek.de/avatar.jpeg"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
I’m Ercan Akyürek, 34 years old, born and raised in Germany with roots in Turkey. From an early age, I was endlessly curious about how things worked, taking apart toys, motors, and gadgets just to see if I could rebuild them again. That curiosity for understanding and creating has been with me ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first real dive into computers came with a VTech learning computer that had a BASIC interpreter. I didn’t know much back then, but I was fascinated by the idea that I could make the machine do something just by typing commands. That curiosity quickly turned into a passion for coding.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>