<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writing a Roller Coaster Simulation on Ercan Akyürek</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/tags/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/</link><description>Recent content in Writing a Roller Coaster Simulation on Ercan Akyürek</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ercanakyuerek.de/tags/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Friction and Air Resistance</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/5-friction-and-air-resistance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/5-friction-and-air-resistance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This chapter will be quite short and introduces two small but important parts of a more realistic roller coaster simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;friction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;air resistance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now our coaster moved in a world without any energy loss. That works for understanding the basics but real coasters slow down over time. Wheels create friction, air pushes against the train, and both effects reduce the acceleration the train can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will not create a complex physics model. Instead we introduce two simple parameters, very similar to what you may know from &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Our physics simulation should behave almost identically, apart from a few edge cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Building the Easiest Possible Track</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/4-building-the-smallest-possible-track/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 11:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/4-building-the-smallest-possible-track/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;To visualize motion properly, we need something for our little object to move along. And that means we need a track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we focus on an extremely simplified roller coaster track. And when I say extremely simplified, I really mean it: it&amp;rsquo;s just a plane. A straight line. A first-order curve. Basically the easiest form of track you can possibly build without accidentally creating a real coaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the last chapter, we know how motion evaluation works. The evaluation function receives an acceleration value and returns a new simulation state containing the updated velocity and the total distance traveled:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Evaluating Motion</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/3-evaluating-motion/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 10:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/3-evaluating-motion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before we implement the function, there&amp;rsquo;s one small simplification we need to mention:
In this chapter we will always evaluate the motion every &lt;strong&gt;16 ms (0.016 seconds)&lt;/strong&gt;,
which corresponds to roughly &lt;strong&gt;60 frames per second&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a fixed time step makes the formulas easier to understand for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: In real simulations or game engines, you usually don’t assume a constant time value. Instead, you take the actual delta time from the game loop, so that the motion stays consistent even if the frame rate changes. &lt;strong&gt;More on that later&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gravity</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/2-gravity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 09:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/2-gravity/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="how-do-we-determine-the-acceleration-of-the-coaster"&gt;How do we determine the acceleration of the coaster?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To simplify things, we ignore air resistance, rolling friction and any other additional forces. We also assume Earth’s gravity is &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s²&lt;/strong&gt;. This allows us to focus entirely on the fundamental idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gravity is the primary source of acceleration.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Earth, gravity provides a constant acceleration of roughly &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s²&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this number actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt;, an object&amp;rsquo;s speed increases by &lt;strong&gt;9.81 m/s&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Introduction and Motion Dynamics</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/1-introduction-and-motion-dynamics/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 08:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/writing-a-roller-coaster-simulation/1-introduction-and-motion-dynamics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You might have played around with JavaScript animations or small physics experiments before, but in this series we are going to take things a step further. We will build a simplified roller coaster simulation directly in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal here isn’t to build some engineering-grade physics engine. I just want to recreate the kind of coaster &lt;strong&gt;physics&lt;/strong&gt; we all know from things like &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster or other coasters in games&lt;/strong&gt;.
Nothing overly scientific, just the kind of system that behaves the way we intuitively expect.
In the end, the physics model will end up pretty close to what &lt;strong&gt;NoLimits Roller Coaster&lt;/strong&gt; does anyway, just without all the heavy engineering baggage.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>