<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Roller Coaster Simulation on Ercan Akyürek</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/tags/roller-coaster-simulation/</link><description>Recent content in Roller Coaster Simulation on Ercan Akyürek</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:30:20 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ercanakyuerek.de/tags/roller-coaster-simulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Improved spline interpolation</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/improved-spline-interpolation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:30:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/improved-spline-interpolation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the latest update, a number of bugs were discovered, particularly in the precision of floating point calculations when working with a web assembly module in a browser environment. It was found that the jitters mentioned earlier were actually caused by a bug in the roll interpolation process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a brief overview, track interpolation involves estimating the length of a NURBS track by interpolating with a large step size and evaluating nodes based on the estimated length, resulting in a dense enough interpolation. After this, the normals are calculated and normal angles are applied on the y and x directions but not on the z direction yet, which is essentially the roll. These normals are then applied to the previous matrix and the process continues. A C2 continuous cubic spline is then constructed, and the z angle, which is the result of applying normals in the x and y directions, is applied on each roll point on top of its roll value. The next step is to iterate through all nodes again and apply rotation on the z direction. Finally, to obtain the matrix at any point, we perform a binary search for the minimum and maximum node whose distance lies between the two and interpolate linearly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>First results</title><link>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/first-results/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 16:28:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ercanakyuerek.de/posts/rollercoaster-simulation/first-results/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of developing an open source roller coaster simulator that is designed to achieve a high degree of compatibility with NoLimits 2. To this end, I have adopted the same track generation and roll interpolation techniques employed by NoLimits 2. Although there are some bugs associated with loading NoLimits2 Parks at present, I anticipate that these issues will be resolved in due course, as I continue to refine the nl2park loader.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>